Massimiliano Russo

Email: m_russo@hms.harvard.edu Homepage: https://rmassimiliano.github.io

ORCID: 0000-0003-4953-9341

Current position

Postdoctoral fellow, Harvard Medical School program in Therapeutic Sciences within the Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science, I am also part of Dr Lorenzo Trippa's group at the Dana-Farber Cancer Institute (DFCI) department of Data Science.

Research interests Analysis and design of clinical trials; Decision theory; Bayesian nonparametrics; Tensor Factorization; Categorical variables; Hierarchical models; Models for Latent Variables; Machine Learning and Data Mining; Computational Statistics.

Education

2015–2019 PhD in Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sci-

Thesis: Bayesian inference for tensor factorization models.

Advisor: Bruno Scarpa

2013-2015 Master in Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Final Mark: 110/110 cum laude,

> Thesis: Olfactory perception differences in Italian regions: a nonparametric Bayesian approach to tensor factorization.

Advisor: Bruno Scarpa; Co-advisor: Giancarlo Ottaviano

2009 - 2013 Bachelor in Statistical and Actuarial sciences, Università degli studi del San-

nio, Benevento, Final Mark: 110/110 cum laude,

Thesis: Multivariate robust estimation. Advisor: Luca Greco

Academic experience

Published Ottaviano, G., Nardello, E., Pendolino, A. L., Pozza, M. D., Russo, M., Savietto, E. Peter, J. A., Ermolao, A., Nasal Function Changes at High Altitude, American Journal of Rhinology & Allergy, 2020.

> Aliverti, E., Paganin, S., Rigon, T. and Russo, M., A discussion on: Latent nested nonparametric priors by Camerlenghi, F., Dunson, D.B., Lijoi, A., Prünster, I. and Rodriguez, A., Bayesian Analysis, 2019+.

> Ottaviano, G., Pendolino, A. L., Nardello, E., Maculan, P., Martini, A., Russo, M. and Lund, V. J., Peak nasal inspiratory flow measurement and visual analogue scale in a large adult population, Clinical Otolaryngology; 44: 541-548, doi:10.1111/coa.13329., 2019.

> Cabassi, A., Casa, A., Fontana, M., Russo, M., and Farcomeni, A., Three testing perspectives on connectome data, Springer Proceedings in Mathematics & Statistics, vol 257, 37-55. Springer, Cham, 2018.

Russo, M., Durante, D. & Scarpa, B., Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, Computational Statistics & Data Analysis. 126, 136-149, 2018.

Cantone E., Ciofalo A., Vodicka J., Iacono V., Mylonakis I., Scarpa B., Russo M., lengo M., de Vincentiis M., Martini A. and Ottaviano G., Pleasantness of olfactory and trigeminal stimulants in different Italian regions., European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology, 1-7, 2017.

Russo, M., Detecting Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, Proceedings the Italian Statistical Society, Firenze University Press, 2017.

Submitted & Russo, M., Ventz, S., Wang, V., Trippa, L., Inference in response-adaptive Under review clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time.

> Aliverti, E. and Russo M., Stratified stochastic variational inference for highdimensional network factor model, arXiv preprint, arxiv.org/abs/2006.14217.

> Russo, M., Singer, B. H. & Dunson, D. B., Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, arXiv preprint, arXiv:1901.05191.

Parallel Computing for big data analysis, March 2018, Specialist lectures during the class of Statistical Methods for Big Data Analysis of Prof. Bruno Scarpa, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Introduction to real analysis (B.Sc.), Year 2014/2015, Academic Tutor, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Advanced statistical inference (M.Sc.), Year 2014/2015, Academic Tutor, University of Padova, Dept. of Statistical Sciences, Padova, Italy.

Conferences Inference in clinical trials when the patient population is subject to & changes over time, Joint Statistical Meeting of the American Statistical Soci-Talks ety, (JSM 2020), (Invited talk).

topic contributed session: "Statistical innovation in regulatory science"

Inference in response-adaptive clinical trials when the enrolled population varies over time, ASA Biopharmaceutical Section Regulatory-Industry Statistics Workshop 2020, (Poster).

Bayesian optimal sequential futility decisions via auxiliary endpoints, International Biometric Conference, (IBC 2020), Accepted for contributed oral Presentation(selected among 700 submissions).

canceled due to COVID-19

Inference in clinical trials when the patient population is subject to changes over time, HiTS Annual Symposium, Boston, MA, USA, October 21, 2019, (Poster).

Soft classification tree ensemble of Higgs pair production, Advanced Statistics for Physics Discovery, Padova, Italy, September 24, 2018, (Poster).

Scalable inference for network factor model, Advanced Statistics for Physics Discovery, Padova, Italy, September 24, 2018, (Speed Talk).

Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, IBC2018, Barcellona, Spain, July 10, 2018, (Contributed talk).

Multivariate mixed membership modeling: Inferring domain-specific risk profiles, ISBA2018, Edinburgh, United Kingdom, June 29, 2018, (Poster).

A multivariate mixed membership model for malaria risk detection, Obayes2017, Austin, Texas, December 11, 2017, (Poster).

Detecting Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, SIS2017, Florence, Italy, June 28, 2017, (Poster).

Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, COBAL V, Cimat, Guanajuato, Mexico, June 8, 2017, (Contributed talk).

Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data, ISBA2016, Sardinia, Italy, June 16, 2016, (Poster).

Workshops **NIMBLE short course**, UC Berkeley, June 2020, (online).

& 3-day workshop on NIMBLE: a system for building and sharing analysis methods for Summer Schools statistical models, especially for hierarchical models and computationally-intensive methods.

Start-Up Research, University of Siena, Italy, June 2017.

A 2-day meeting where groups of young scholars, advised by senior researchers, were asked to develop innovative methods and models to analyze a common dataset from the Neurosciences.

Data Hackathons Duke Datathon, Durham, NC, USA, February 2017.

Stats under the stars-3, Firenze, Italy, June 2017.

Stats under the stars, Padova, Italy, September 2015.

Reviewer for: Journal of Computational Methods in Sciences and Engineering (JCMSE); Computational Statistics and Data Analysis (CSDA); European Symposium on Artificial Neural Networks (ESANN) 2020; Social Indicator Research; Statistical Methods & Applications (SMA); Trials.

Memberships International Society for Bayesian Analysis (ISBA)

Outreach & events Regsci Forum: Fellows Showcase. What the Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science actually does? Wonder no more! (January 2020)

Research presentation to describe the world of regulatory science to students.

Big data Biosensori e Biobanche, December 2019

Presentation of my research at University degli Study del Sannio .

Harvard-MIT Center for Regulatory Science Open House: Learn about RegSci and research opportunity. (September 2019)

Meeting with Harvard graduate students to discuss research opportunities.

Volunteer for Venetonight - La notte dei ricercatori, Padova, Italy. (2015,2016 & 2017)

Developed an online app interfacing with twitter to track and display in real-time the sentiment of the event.

Volunteer for StatisitcAll, Treviso, Italy (2015)

Statistical games and activities to show the magic of statistics to kids and adults.

Volunteer at orientation days for high schools students, Scegli con noi. Campus Agripolis di Legnaro, Padova, Italy. (2015 & 2016)

Awards

Best paper award for "Bayesian Inference on Group Differences in Multivariate Categorical Data" Dept. of Statistical Sciences, University of Padova (Research Prize 2018)

Winner of the 3 minutes thesis competition selection of Dept. of Statistical Sciences, University of Padova, October 19, 2018.

Young researcher travel award ISBA2018, Edinburgh, United Kingdom. Travel support for COBAL V (2017), Guanajuato, Mexico Young researcher travel award ISBA2016, Sardinia, Italy.

Work experience

Feb. 2019 – Aug. 2019 Data Analyst, WorkFor, WFIT CRM Services, Roma.

Data analysis and consulting.

Study visits

Nov. 2016 - June 2017 Visiting Research Scholar, Duke University, Department of Statistical Science,

Sept. 2017 - Mar. 2018 Durham, NC, USA, under the supervision of prof. David B. Dunson.

Languages

Italian: native; English: fluent; French: basic; Spanish: basic.

Computing skills

Programming languages R: advanced knowledge of Rcpp, tidyverse and shiny libraries;

C/C++,Python, Julia, Matlab, JAVA.

Operative System Linux (Fedora/Ubuntu), Windows, OSX and relative softwares.

Software SPSS, PSPP, Office, SQL/MYSQL,Bugs,Jags,Stan, and Nimble.

Other LATEX, git/github, vim & emacs, bash.

In compliance with the Italian Decree 196 dated 30/06/2003, I hereby authorize the recipient of this document to use and process my personal data

5 July 2020